this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is the Amidah
Spinelli's for software engineering
radio today I have with me mark Hoffman
and I will be talking with him on code
coverage analysis and the jacoco tool
mark Hoffman is considered the leading
expert in byte code coverage analysis
mark wrote a Clemmie a free java code
coverage tool for eclipse which one the
best open source a clip based developer
tool community award in 2008 later mark
started the jacoco project as a modern
code coverage back-end for e clement and
other tools which is now widely used as
code coverage engine including for open
JDK development for his contributions to
the community mark was recognized as a
java champion in 2014 mark welcome to
software engineering radio hello the
midis thank you for having me here today
what is code coverage analysis why it's
a dynamic metric so you will execute a
piece of code or your application under
test and record the pieces of code which
has been executed mm-hmm like which line
of code which branches has been taken
which instructions so you get an
detailed metrics of what has been
executed you typically use that for
automated tests so to believe a unit
tests you have a unit test suite and the
coverage analysis tells you something
about the quality of your unit tests
especially the completeness so what
parts of the your code base has been
executed by your test suite and why is
this useful to know what this gives you
an good idea especially about the
untested parts of your code base so you
can identify the places which meet need
more testing where you should write more
tests and have a
mmm have a look at him maybe there's a
chance to also delete code so and this
is maybe the code is not required at all
so it helps you to keep your codebase
clean and test it in projects how will
the project typically use code coverage
and the test coverage analysis first of
all you need to somehow integrate it
into your tool chain so the simplest way
is that you have the tool the code
coverage to directly running it your IDE
mm-hmm so most ideas like eclipse
support code coverage out of the box
today
okay tips for example is now back to if
we you Clemmie plugin our first plugin
which is now part of the Eclipse
platform this is the simplest way to get
started but then you should really
thinking about making it part of your
continuous integration pipeline so make
it part of for example you may even
build and integrate it here Gradle all
of the build systems have integrations
for code coverage nowadays so you can
continuously monitor the code coverage
and you might also put a tool on top of
it for example sonar cube to get like a
time series how your code base evolves
regarding respect to various metrics one
of them might be called coverage AHA so
often in continuous integration you you
have something that fails the continuous
integration do you have a specific limit
regarding code coverage do you have a
metric and the value that you using for
that purpose actually I'm I get this
Kerstin quite a lot so what is the good
percentage or whatever the issue here is
that the fact that a particular piece of
code has been covered only means it has
been executed
there's no no meaning about the the the
quality and the value of the test for
example think about unit tests which
simply invoke code but they do not have
any assertions and this is what you
really want to avoid in your project so
my typical advice is to keep an eye on
the untested code so where do you have
areas of untested code in your co-pays
and think about how you can add valuable
tests to this untested code or maybe
think about translating this code maybe
it's not necessary
anymore so what I recommend teams
typically is not care about percentage
but care about the total amount of
untested code and over the course of the
time make sure that the amount of
untested code the absolute amount of a
untested code does not increase thus the
developer should look at the code that
has not been tested in a qualitative
manner and see what type of code it is
and whether additional tests are needed
that's your advice
absolutely and keep an eye on the
untested code so don't rely on the fact
that you have like 80 or 90% code
coverage because the the the unit test
could be useless and especially if you
have like and if you create like a
competition between teams and if you
make it a management matrix there's
always the possibility that developers
start writing useless unit tests just
for the sake of the metric so this is
local optimization this doesn't make
sense it happens with many metrics and
can it will allow you to see such things
such gaming or is it just the result of
bad management focused and there's
nothing that can be done no no the code
the tool or let the pure code coverage
tool cannot tell you about that there
are other tools like mutation testing
mutation testing actually checks whether
the the unit tests checks the behavior
of your code so a mutation testing which
is kinda expensive metric you modify the
code under test for example you change
boundary checks in the production code
on the fly
and the tool verifies that the
corresponding test will fail so if you
can for example replace a less than
operator with a greater than operator
and there's no test failing this means
that your test suite is probably not not
complete on there's no proper validation
and it's not exercising that code as it
should be it's not properly tested
maybe it's exodus maybe it's exercising
but it doesn't care about the result
because he completely inverted the
meaning of the condition and nobody was
noticing it so that's that's a more
available
a metric but it's it's depending on how
your exercise is a very expensive metric
and takes a long time to actually
execute a bit such metrics mm-hmm and
continuing on metrics have two questions
first of all there are also multiple
understand metrics for code coverage so
source function statement branches
conditions and so on is other particular
things you should be aiming for those
metrics or in journey you are looking at
just code and untested code okay there's
a it depends a bit on your use case no
obviously what it's very easy to
understand like line coverage so you can
think of lines of source code and
everybody can think about this and this
is like a very simple metric but there
are more advanced metrics i really
recommend to have a look at for example
cyclomatic complexity this is an old
formal definition which basically gives
you an idea about the number of
independent test cases you need to test
a specific method so if you a method has
the chromatic complexity of five you
need at least five independent test
cases to make sure all branches and all
paths within the methods or execute
executed mm-hmm
this is quite interesting so we
interested in integrated this in Shikoku
and provide a metric which is called
like missed complexity covered
complexity or miss complexity so if our
method given from the example with
complexity five has a missed complexity
of two this means there are two unit
tests missing and this is quite
interesting if you have like a large
projects and you see like okay to get
full coverage the miss complexity is
around let's say 500 this means it would
cost you to write 500 unit tests to get
full coverage on this project so you
know the amount of work that is required
right right and full coverage is
something that we should be aiming for
not as a metric but as a goal is that
right No
the approaches there is it depends on
the approach so if you have it it's nice
but just to do it for the sake of
coverage this typically leads to
completely useless unit test this is
what I was talking yes before but if the
process is this that you've worked in a
complete a test driven way and you
always test first so whenever you fix a
park
you've right to reproduce the first
which is a unit test if you implant in
you feature a new component you always
write the test first this is this is
definitely the best process you can
follow and this is what I always
recommend to do this because you beside
code coverage you get other benefits in
respect of in in terms of quality for
your code base if you write unit tests
first think of the unit test is the
first client of your API so if it even
if you design an API of a component the
unit test is first verification whether
the API is usable no matter the API
makes actually sense and if you follow
that process you will arrive at full
test coverage but as a result of the
process not as an explicit goal right
absolutely absolutely this is and you
get more value than just code coverage
code coverage as such as no value to
your project mm-hmm I think this
something our listeners will appreciate
as an insight other some examples from
industries or projects that achieve high
coverage or where a high coverage is
required of course there's like in
industry like railroad which deal with
safety components of safety relevance of
the components or in airplanes
there's also specifications which
require a certain or full coverage or
full test coverage of code but it is not
what we can provide with the Java
tooling because the Java platform itself
is not certified for such environments
so you need a certified tool for that
and a very restricted runtime
environment so all the dynamic like
memory allocation what we have in shower
is not allowed in these requirements in
these environments and to finish up with
a
coverage discussion is there a sweet
spot that we would say that additional
coverage is a lot of effort with minimal
benefits say something like 80 percent
or something it depends on the project
or is there situation another way to
judge when you have enough testing
rather than into intuition as we
discussed earlier well it depends on the
nature of the tested code so what I
always recommend is to separate or your
split your components and components
which are weld unit testable especially
your business logic so on the core value
of your application and separate this
clearly from I would say glue code for
example to wire to let's say a database
connectivity or to the file system and I
always recommend to provide abstractions
for example for file system access or
database access mm-hmm so you can try
the real unit tests for the core part of
the application without having a
database in the backend and for the glue
code as such it's probably not that well
be able to spend too much with unit
tests and and mocking on on on such code
so here I recommend really try to do
integration test so make sure that the
glue code and the whole application
actually works is a real database but
this is a different test set then mm-hmm
and test coverage more useful for
exercising and looking at your unique
that the value of your unit tests or is
not important for integration testing
for unit tests I think this is a primary
value for integration testing
integration tests always should be
featured rhythm so your software
application has a certain set of
features and you should have a clear
mapping between your integration tests
and your feature so you have the proof
that a particular features has actually
been tested when you're down in on on
unit tests on the level of unit tests
the components your testing is like Java
classes and typically it's pretty tough
to map the single Java class to a
feature to your application so
it's more about functional coverage when
it comes to component testing but still
it's a nice metric to look at for
example you still can identify areas in
your code or maybe modules which are not
tested at all with your component tests
so you might identify use cases which
has been messed missed in the test
scenarios so you add new test scenarios
in order to exercise those right and
moving down to specific methods in Java
have often exception handling try catch
blocks how do you deal with that do you
typically do you find useful to add it
in tested code coverage both in the code
and the part that deals with the
exceptions or is it very difficult to do
that that's a that's an interesting
question first of all it's difficult to
do it if you want to do it you need to
have proper abstractions and you need to
be able to mark for example the analyze
underlying system to emulate the
exception so for example let's say where
you have like a database driver and
there's a connectivity problem whatever
then you need to find a way to mock the
database driver and actually simulate
this exception but this is actually
something you really should focus on not
only in testing also in the design how
you anticipate failure but we've seen a
lot and system is that the actual error
handling is the least tested part and
that the original error like let's say a
broken database connection is not the
problem the problem is the broken error
handling in your application let's say
you have like a webshop whatever and
there's a spontaneous database
connection drop and one user might get
an error if he let's say performs a
certain operation but what then
typically happens that the the actual
error handling causes much more damage
for example by doing endless retries and
breaks down the whole system this is
what we've seen a lot in the
so error handling is quite critical and
actually testing it especially
integration testing it this is what I
recommend mmm
so it's back to integration testing
absolutely absolutely right let's turn
our focus on tools which are as you said
very important for test coverage how are
exactly tools used to achieve test
coverage what are the specific steps one
should take in order to utilize the
tools for measuring test coverage okay
and maybe I tell you about the the
technical background there's our test
coverage actually measured and we can
see how this actually is integrated in
various tools so what the trick here is
the shukaku code coverage tool is
completely based on Java byte code so
the only input it needs is your class
files it could be in charge and Wars for
every binaries mm-hmm binary the
compiled binary so we don't care about
the source code at all this bytecode is
so-called instrumented instrumentation
means that the control flow within your
code if in the method is inspected and
additional code is inserted we call it
is called probes and pro pre-course the
fact that a certain piece of kotas has
been executed and from this information
we can in fear the coverage of every
line every instruction every branch so
this is a trick behind it to do this
modification we use a hook and the JVM
which is called the Java agent the Java
agent is a extension to the JVM you can
load it start up typically specify to my
other command line and this agent allows
various interaction with the JVM and one
possible interaction is to transform the
binary class files before they are
actually loaded in the JVM and this is
where we hook in so the first and only
point of integration to measure code
coverage for an application is to
specify this Shikoku Java agent which is
basically a small command-line option
and to do this you can just do this
manually on the command line for example
if you start an applique
Asian server but all of our tools
provide little utilities which provide
the correct syntax for you and edit to
the respective configuration for example
if you have a maven build and fuse may
be surefire to run your unit tests the
the chikaku maven goal will prepare a
specific property for the surefire
runner to add this Chicago agent to to
it to your build and this is the first
part this is maybe the simple part but
Haku them produces is an saga die so
called execution data file mm-hmm which
is again a binary file where the
information about execution of the
probes is persisted and in the second
step you want to create a nice report
like HTML report X in a report and you
want to see the total figures and here
you need another tool which is the
report generator which takes the
execution data file and the original
class files and creates a report out of
this and for typically for example for
maven we have two tools one tool is a
tool is in case of maven is called
prepare agent which it's the agent to
your runtime at the before you start
your test and the second step is then
create a report out of the data which
has been gathered at write them and this
is basically the integration you do with
every tool and for example for the
Eclipse IDE this is completely hidden by
the clemmer plugin so the akuma plugin
does all the magic for you and behinds
of a new lounge any kind of travel
program in coverage mode the Java agent
is automatically added to the command
line that is fired in the background
mm-hmm and is this running cumulative so
if you run multiple instances of your
application are the results collated
together how do you clear the results
between runs or when you decide to have
changed the code by default the video
start the new Trivium the agent assume
nothing is executed for sure
it has no memory about previous runs but
if you specify the same execution data
file for multiple runs the data will be
accumulated so somehow your your tool
looks at the executed file determines if
it is the same or not and if it is the
same it accumulates the data
it simply appends new data to the
existing file and once you create a
report report generator then it reads in
the execution data file it simply adds
all the data which is found in the file
source as simple as adding a pending new
data to the existing file there's the
test average code interfere with the
measurement of the metric so you don't
care you treat it as any other code no
it does not interfere with the original
Java code so it should not have the
should not change the behavior of the
code this of course is would be a bug
that should be reported immediately and
I don't think we have that but there's
some interference with other tools which
also use on-the-fly bytecode
instrumentation so they get into you
can't oriented to its way specifically
for Chikako the issue is that we need to
classifies at two places at run time to
actually instrument them and insert the
probes in later on at analysis time I've
read made more information out of the
class time for transferred for example
the debug information so we can in fear
line coverage so we get the line
coverage of which line has been executed
from the debug information and for this
purpose that is quite critical that we
see the same class file at execution
time and at runtime so imagine there's
different set of methods at the file at
execution time then at the file analysis
time we can not match the data and
here's the critical part some tours
actually also modify the the class files
and change the structure of the class
files for example at new methods to it
and then so there Takako runtime sees a
different
file then the Shikoku report generator
and this causes actually problems and a
good reflection also be a problem or is
it transparently handled in our
reflections not a problem at all
reflection does not change the the
structure of a classifier so you can
access the members in the fields but you
can net more you cannot modify the
structure or the behavior of a chav a
class definition with reflections is
this is not an issue for us but about if
you call a method by a reflection yes it
will also be it will be shown as covered
like it would be a normal call you
mentioned that the jacoco is used by
maven and Eclipse other ideas that
support jacoco and if environments sure
so we have so at least we know about I
think 15 integrations and commercials
and non-commercial tools so the
integration suite or not on our own
there's basically integration for every
for every Idid like NetBeans or IntelliJ
they all have integrations for that but
not you're not providing this
integration the IDE vendors itself
picked up Shikoku as a tool mm-hmm and
you also mentioned the shown R cube and
they are easy to also used by other
similar frameworks environments I don't
know exactly what close source tools are
into using it but I now for example
about team city or urban code or a so
visual studio team services these
commercial tools also provide deaf ports
and for the continuous integrations or
continuous integration services and they
also use Takako as far as I know mm-hmm
are there other tools in this space in
metal code coverage analysis for Java
I'm sure sure there's the the other byte
code base code coverage tool this is
called cobertura which is also quite old
it uses basically the same principles
then jacoco does and then there's source
code is instrumentation based tool which
means the source code is modified
rather than the bytecode the right
and which is clever it was a commercial
product by Atlassian but just recently
they went open source of it it's called
open open clevon and now I think you can
find it on Oakland clavata oh and this
is the original source base no provided
for the community and it's still
maintained by the original source and
it's pretty nice too they offer
something like test coverage so you can
have a traceability between a specific
unit test and the lines touched by this
unit test which cannot be done through a
binary mr. mutation I think it could be
done yes we are targeting large-scale
[Music]
products and like price of like 1
million lines of code or let's say
100,000 unit tests and up to now we
haven't found a clever data model to
have a scalable model to store per test
coverage for such projects with out and
relevant decrease in performance and
this is probably the the main benefit of
jacoco that they there's literally no
performance regression if you run check
Hoku and you're built I was about to ask
you about how does one choose a tool to
use for cartridge analysis and where
their drawbacks were advantages specific
tools or approaches a sure they are so
one thing is like the the runtime
footprint so how much for example does
it slow down your your billet or your
test execution this is one thing you
should look at the other thing is of
course the feature sets or what features
do you actually need but that's one
crucial thing this is also the supporter
JDK versions so over the new Karan's of
JDK releases for the tool vendors is
pretty tough to provide support for the
latest Java runtimes and we are pretty
eager to catch up with the JDK release
schedule we are working closely together
with the open JDK project and we just
recently released support for Java
ten so just a couple of days after the
official release was announced but it's
tough to keep up with a new release you
need to adjust the instrumentation for
every new JVM release it's very tough
the issue is that so with Java
traditionally the specification is
released with the implementation so we
don't have a time frame to adapt to the
new features before we see the final
release so most likely there's not many
changes at the end of 3 or just before
the release but still we don't have a
formal specification of the new bytecode
formats before we see a release and also
the for example the tohoku library also
needs a builds deck so we also use tools
like maven to build the library so and
here we have a chicken-egg problem you
know I mean we don't have the tools yet
for Java 10 available but people expect
us to release a library for Java 10 and
when you say release jai-alai before job
that does it mean that it will support
the new features of Java 10 or it will
not run at all unless you have the new
version of the library so is our the new
release of JVM breaking the existing
tools and the support that you have the
instrumentation for bytecode
you get it so the minimum issue you have
that you get a new pod code version the
openjdk project decided to increment the
bytecode version with every release so
there's no semantics there's no semantic
versioning so if every release we need
to understand a new version of bytecode
this is typically only a header
information this is the easy case
because it's just about a new number we
have to understand in the header but the
interesting cases and there's new
functionality in the bytecode for
example new op codes or new structures a
new way how to invoke methods or for
example if we got a list of eight we got
methods default methods and interfaces
and these are things we need to deal
with of course with the Java code
coverage tool Java cocoa also work with
other languages that create JVM
of course Chicago does not care about
the source language which only cares
about classifiers and whatever runs on
the JVM you can create code coverage for
it and it actually works pretty well
with many other jvm languages let's say
like Ruby or Lombok more long bog it's
not our language one zone of course is
just a notation framework it also works
in Cortland for example we have a
repository with a long list of different
jvm languages with examples the issue
here is that many of these are
especially high level programming
languages like Ruby they produce a lot
of synthetic methods like they trade
additional methods additional code that
is created by the compiler and you might
see this code as uncovered so the
metrics you get out of for these
languages might not be that what you
expect so we currently working with this
on this with the respective program
projects for example of groovy and they
help us they create annotations class
visible annotations which mark bytecode
which is generated so we can easily
exclude this bytecode from the reports
and then you need to adapt for each
language have some adaptation layer you
know at a reporting level right right
right so once the language like a groovy
agreed on a specific annotation we
unfortunately there's no standard
specification but that is a problem
there sanitation in the java jdk which
is called generated unfortunately this
generated annotation has retention
source code so once it's compiled to a
classifier this annotations not visible
anymore it's not included in the class
file anymore and this is the problem why
we cannot use the standard of annotation
would be nice to use it but all the
languages created their own application
what we their own annotation and what we
basically do we add filters for this
annotation to Chicago we have this for
example for Kotlin we have two so groovy
we're waiting on we have this for Lombok
we have it for groovy but for example
we're still waiting
getting such annotation or such an hint
for the Kotlin language that would be
really nice and cotton users are really
expecting to use code coverage tools
also on cotton so it seems that it's
there's a great benefit in working with
byte code because you can cover more
languages are there any advantages in
working with source code in source code
so the the granularity if you make but
back to source code is just line level
so we know whether particular line has
been executed or not we know the the
bytecode instructions from that line but
we don't know about the internals of the
line so let's think about boolean
expressions for several parts in a
single line we can hardly interfere
which parts of this expression has been
executed because by default the chair
compiler only emits debug information on
line granularity so if you work on
source code instrumentation you can of
course instrument the line and add
probes with might be probes within a
single line for example to know which
parts of the source code has been of
this piece of line has been executed
exactly so this is one of the benefits
if you do a source instrumentation but
on the other hand the tropic is that
integration in your tool stick is very
harder because you have to cut in and
before you actually compile your source
code you have to create a copy of your
source code instrumented and then
compile it so you get artifacts for the
purpose of code coverage only with the
Clemmie approach especially with the
on-the-fly instrumentation you can at
code coverage code coverage very late in
your chain you can even attach an agent
to an existing productive system and
measure code coverage under productive
systems which some people do mm-hmm as a
Java champion did you ever ask for
specific directions in the JDK
development no to improve the code
coverage analysis or is everything you
want it has always been there no so
actually there's some City Kay comes
with its own or internally used code
coverage tool uses check off and there's
some interesting
experiments they're doing for example
they have an option in the compiler to
create additional annotations with
source code mapping within the line so
this is something we could facilitate in
Shikoku in future if we get this as
default for the Java compilers what we
actually do we work very close with the
open JDK project especially if they
break some of our functionality this
sometimes happens we have a nice
integration test suite which means we
compile different pieces of source code
run a unit test on it and see whether we
get the expected coverage and this test
suite which is quite big in the meantime
release revealed quite a few bugs in new
Cherokee releases and we work very
closely with the open trade Kay project
to report these issues and they take our
reports cry very serious and we get very
quick turnarounds and feedback on these
issues I think in the meantime be one of
the top backcountry external bug
contributors of the JDK project let me
get this earth how what is the process
in which you uncover those bugs it's an
integration test suite which involves
two parts of the JDK the compiler and of
course the Java Runtime and from our
perspective we want to see whether the
code coverage tool shikoku actually
produces the expected results from the
perspective or code coverage but
implicitly we're testing the compiler
and the Java Runtime so for example we
uncovered errors in the line mapping
table so the mapping from the bytecode
back to the source code sometimes if
they do optimizations and the compiler
this mapping is broken and this is what
we immediately uncover with our test
suite because the expected results it's
not what we defined in our test in or
test setup and so we quickly identify
such problems for example and the Java
compiler the other thing is that we have
a lot of tests for a
say corner cases of the Java
specification of the Java byte code
specification and please for example
sometimes see crashes of the Java
Runtime with certain corner cases in the
in the bytecode
structure and this is also what we
constantly report amazing though when
developers see very important what form
is a report produced is integrated with
the ID does the ID highlight code
sections that are not covered
this is a typical integration for the
IDS so I can speak here for the Eclipse
integration so here you see you get
threes live overview you can drill down
from project to package level down to
class level but you also get
highlighting directly in the editor so
you seek like a colored highlighting of
the colored or missed lines within your
text editor it's not a separate view
it's the same text area you can just
keep editing in the same editor in the
same editor you see annotations for
branches you get tooltips about the
branch coverage status you can also
integrate it in your standard fuels like
your project Explorer or whatever and
you get annotations there with the
covers you can configure that within
your idea ever you want to see the code
coverage you can property dialogues on
every Java element and see overview of
code coverage of that elementor's
Eclipse officer nice set of extension
points to hook into the IDE and present
information right there right where the
user expects it
yep assume you want to city also the
whole project or in a class or a
specific method and then drill down to
code right yeah this is exactly how how
it works in the IDE for the tools for a
report the report works very similar as
for example the HTML report you get in
three of your project structure down to
package down to classes down to method
and this is like a tabular view and then
you can jump right in the source code
and you can see the highlighted source
code which pretty much looks like within
the idea of course you can not edit it
and it's a read-only report right and
when you go to
continuous integration pipeline is there
a way to turn red when something happens
when they percent declines or the
coverage less than a level how do people
usually do the coverage and integrate it
with their continuous integration and so
we provide tools for that for the Maven
or for the ant
integration we have check goals their
users can specify certain metrics for
example a given percentage on line
coverage or maybe an absolute number so
let's like I said say there must be not
more than five classic routes or not
covered at all you can specify a lot of
limits which are then tested during the
build and you can fail actually the
build if these minimum numbers are not
reached and you mentioned this are per
class or in terms of line numbers
percentage what are the most useful or
which one would do you typically use in
your projects actually I do not
recommend to use these checks at all to
be honest what you can do is you can do
it as like it's like a sanity check so
you do like okay maybe in the project we
have let's say 80% code coverage or 90%
coverage then I would do a check of
let's say 50 or 60 percent so way below
then the current the current coverage so
we have like a sanity check to make sure
that the tests are actually executed and
the code coverage has been implemented
probably because some temperatures can
break so we have like a green build but
it's just because your tests have not
been executed at all so you have some
confidence that most of your tests has
actually been executed but if you really
want to monitor the the code coverage I
don't recommend to set limits which are
like really just below the current
status for this I really recommend using
a tool like sonic qube to keep track of
your coverage over time how is that
different from integrating needing to
they continue to the gradation pipeline
you can integrate it for example the
Jenkins plugin for Shikoku this also
gives you a kind of a timeline so you
can actually produce powers but for the
build itself so for the for the main bit
for example
I wouldn't try to update always update
the check and I just always a chance to
limit so the latest status of your
project and whenever you are heaved
let's say 1% more of court coverage to
adjust the limit again this does not
really add value to your project whereas
with Sonic you see overall trends and
you may be spot things that are going
the right or the wrong direction and you
get you can relate it to two other
metrics for example you get code
coverage on new code so sonic qube
consumes a lot of inputs for example
also the change history of your code so
to knock you knows which is the coverage
of new code in a given time frame so if
you have a huge legacy code base you
don't maybe you don't care about over a
code coverage because the project is
just too big but the teams are working
on some small areas for new features and
you want to monitor the new code for
example this is something what
continuous inspection tools give you can
you elaborate please a bit more about
the Phantom inspection tools and how
they work with code coverage continues
inspection monitors the several aspects
of your of your code base for example
rules whether the coding guidelines are
followed or there's a lot of rules about
typical
coding errors with static analysis you
can recognize for example a resource
let's say input stream has been created
but it's not closed these are all rules
which can be identified by such
continuous inspection tours and they
give you an overall overview of the
quality of your project and code
coverage is just a piece or just an
aspect of the overall quality of your
project mm-hmm you mentioned that the
jacoco itself is using a Joe Cocker to
measure coverage at the gates coverage
from the very beginning so this was when
i when i created shikoku as a prototype
from the beginning i was thinking about
releasing it this open source project
but my personal milestone was i will
release it as soon as i can create
coverage for chikaku it's
then that we can be released and this is
was actually the case from the very
first release which was zero that 1.0 is
somewhere back in 2009 and that what
level was the coverage what is it now
it's still somewhere around 95 or 98
percent so Turkic was fully test driven
the number of use cases and the
complexity of the integration is simply
in a scale that therefore the small team
it would be completely impossible to do
manual testing on this tool so we
heavily rely on the unit tests and
integration tests we have for Shikoku
and whatever we do let's say bug fixes
let's say new features is always test
first so we always think about test
strategy and we think about how to
approve that the functionality actually
works and this is the only way how we
add features and this is very tough for
our contributors because sometimes we
can point contributions without any
tests and we don't we cannot accept such
contributions it will simply add too
much technical test to to our project if
we have features which we cannot prove
that they are working these are very
wise words do you happen to know the
cabbage and ice of a openjdk is it
measured with make sense to measure it
as far as I know they do they have their
own tool called Jake Huff and they
measure they they keep an eye on code
covers as far as I know but the tool I
have now used the tool I think it's
pretty tough to use it outside the open
JDK project so I can not judge about the
tool or how it's actually used by the
open JDK project I'm not very familiar
with therapy build pipeline and their
continuous integration pipeline open JDK
is not that openness then son I might
suggest yes they always they built
structure and how the project internally
builds and what it requires is can often
be a difficult part for a project to
Excel contribution be truly open do you
happen to know other figures from other
projects so the average figures so that
our listeners can get a feeling of where
they should aim at so what we typically
see is so a project which really does
test-driven
development they always end up beyond
the idea 90% test coverage if they have
the right process to think about testing
first create the test first and then
actually write the code do you have too
many interesting bugs you have uncovered
by crazing test coverage something
that's particularly stayed in your mind
it's not right now it's as I said before
like if you into one to increase the the
test coverage after the fact you lose a
lot of benefits like trading correct
code from the beginning or creating
proper api's this is all benefits if
your practice test first so adding code
craft which after the fact to our
project is always tough especially if
the structure of the project does not
allow so if the project does not
actually have real components if it's
like just one huge block of
interconnected components and you cannot
isolate single parts to test those parts
so testing or adding coverage after the
fact is something I really don't
recommend and mmm which is like really
tough and typically it goes along with
refactoring the original code based who
have actually testable components and of
course the project will not have
testable components because it was not
implemented in a way that would that
move together with unit tests so it's
right right right though things go
together
I think robots associated with the
tracking code coverage you mentioned
about gaming the metrics other things
people should look out for no it's
actually it's basically about setting up
wrong expectations and just looking for
for for code coverage metrics also what
I have seen which is which I consider
very dangerous because I don't you lose
all the benefits of test first that unit
tests are created by separate teams like
you have like an offshore team and the
offshore team is just responsible to add
unit tests to some code base and this is
like really this is not about how you do
it so this will not add any quality to
your original code it sounds really
misguided but I can really imagine
companies doing it yes but this is a
fact this is this is a matter of fact
I know projects which work exactly like
this and I would really not do it this
way not at all
Dilbert comes out of real life it's not
this imaginary so what should I tell my
managers to persuade them to adopt test
coverage analysis don't don't tell them
at all
don't tell just do it just do it for
your team just heaven working agreement
within your team that you do test first
but don't make it an official metric so
this is what I always tell them I talk
so don't tell your management's about
code coverage just do it and keep an eye
of it they will track it in there they
will make it a metric trackable metric
and then it will lose value because
people will manipulate it absolutely
this is this is what will happen if it's
a management metrics then it's an easy
metrics yeah just a number and it's
easier to understand for management but
it will not at value if there's no
proper process behind that mm-hmm
mark is there anything else I should
have asked you about didn't something
you would like to share with our
listeners maybe about new Java versions
and challenges with Union they need the
new Java versions mm-hmm so what are the
challenges of new Java versions but if
you have with the latest Java versions
or maybe even shorten with Java 7 Java 8
is that we do code coverage and Java
bytecode and and the early travel
versions like saying till Java 5 for
Java 6 there was a one-to-one
relationship between source code and
bytecode so we could easily map that
just the bytecode to the source code
with new versions we see new
synthetically sugars something like
lambda or something like try with
resources and for this the mapping is
not as simple anymore but what because
what the computing a project is a
project decided is to put more
functionality into the compiler so
things like try with resources ends up
in a complex nested structure of try
finally blocks in the class file and the
issue a we have of the code coverage
tool to map back or to recognize these
structures in the in in the class files
and map it back to the source code
during the
reporting time and this is getting more
and more tricky with the travel language
in the new features of the travel
English hmm is byte code is just in time
compilation creating any additional
problems no we're working on byte code
level and just in time compilation goes
down to the machine code so just the
time compilations kicks in after we
instrumented the the byte code this is
for the for the structure but what we
actually see if you have a library which
just like real number crunching we can
see some performance regressions here
because due to the additional probes for
example inlining is disabled because the
method is growing so if you have like a
simple set on gather which is typically
in line by the just-in-time compiler
after instrumentation with jacoco the
method and byte code level growth too
big to be in line so this is the only
point where we interfere with
just-in-time compilers that due to the
increased size of the methods we see
some performance drops especially and
hotspots there's a lot of execution on
small and tiny messes
mark thank you very much for being with
us what can listeners find out more
about the topics we discussed of course
on the chaco co.org website so there is
complete documentation this is one thing
we try to do so it's not just test first
you also to documentation first so
whatever the edits and features the
documentation will be updated and we try
to provide a consistent view or on the
tool from the documentation on the
functionality point of view also on the
website you find you will find a long
list of conference talks and
presentation we have done especially
also afghani monthly cough was main
contributor to the project there's a lot
of funny and interesting presentations
about how to use it and about also about
implementation details so you can learn
about how it is implemented and what are
the what are the tricky parts within you
JDK versions for example yeah sure
excellent thank you again ok thank you
thank you for having me here today this
is the Amidah Spinelli's for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to se Radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening